<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:cerif="http://eurocris.org/ontology/cerif/0.1#" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:bibo="http://purl.org/ontology/bibo/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:org="http://www.w3.org/ns/org#" xmlns:CLV="https://w3id.org/italia/onto/CLV" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#">

	<foaf:Person rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/person/luigi_asprino">

		<!-- Informazioni Personali -->
		<foaf:givenname>Luigi</foaf:givenname>
		<foaf:family_name>Asprino</foaf:family_name>
		<foaf:img rdf:resource="http://luigiasprino.it/img/luigi-asprino.jpg" />
		<foaf:mbox rdf:resource="mailto:luigi.asprino@istc.cnr.it" />
		<foaf:homepage rdf:resource="http://luigiasprino.it" />
		<foaf:account>
			<foaf:OnlineAccount>
				<foaf:accountServiceHomepage rdf:resource="https://orcid.org/" />
				<foaf:accountName>0000-0003-1907-0677</foaf:accountName>
			</foaf:OnlineAccount>
		</foaf:account>

		<!-- Affiliazione -->
		<org:memberOf>
			<org:Organization rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/organization/istc">
				<foaf:name>Istituto di Scienze e Tecnologie della Cognizione</foaf:name>
				<foaf:acronym>ISTC</foaf:acronym>
				<org:hasSite>
					<org:Site geo:lat="41.905973" geo:long="12.504686">
						<CLV:hasAddress>
							<CLV:Address>
								<CLV:fullAddress>Via San Martino della Battaglia, 44, 00185 Roma, Italia</CLV:fullAddress>
							</CLV:Address>
						</CLV:hasAddress>
					</org:Site>
				</org:hasSite>
			</org:Organization>
		</org:memberOf>

		<!-- Publicazioni -->
		<foaf:made rdf:resource="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/publication/Asprino2018Empirical" />
		<foaf:made rdf:resource="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/publication/Lodi2017Semantic" />

		<!-- Projects -->
		<foaf:currentProject rdf:resource="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/project/ecodigit" />

	</foaf:Person>




	<bibo:Article rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/publication/Asprino2018Empirical" dc:language="en" bibo:pageStart="3962" bibo:pageEnd="3969" bibo:doi="10.24963/ijcai.2018/551" dc:date="2018" dc:title="Empirical Analysis of Foundational Distinctions in Linked Open Data">

		<dcterms:isPartOf>
			<bibo:Proceedings rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/publication/IJCAI2018" dc:title="Proceedings of the 27th International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence and the 23rd European Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI-ECAI-18)" bibo:issn="978-0-9992411-2-7" />
		</dcterms:isPartOf>

		<bibo:abstract>
			The Web and its Semantic extension (i.e. Linked Open Data) contain open global-scale knowledge and make it available to potentially intelligent machines that want to benefit from it. Nevertheless, most of Linked Open Data lack ontological distinctions and have sparse axiomatisation. For example, distinctions such as whether an entity is \emph{inherently} a class or an individual, or whether it is a physical object or not, are hardly expressed in the data, although they have been largely studied and formalised by foundational ontologies (e.g. DOLCE, SUMO). These distinctions belong to common sense too, which is relevant for many artificial intelligence tasks such as natural language understanding, scene recognition, and the like. There is a gap between foundational
			ontologies, that often formalise or are inspired by pre-existing philosophical theories and are developed with a top-down approach, and Linked Open Data that mostly derive from existing databases or crowd-based effort (e.g. DBpedia, Wikidata). We investigate whether machines can learn foundational distinctions over Linked Open Data entities, and if they match common sense. We want to answer questions such as ``does the DBpedia entity for \emph{dog} refer to a class or to an instance?". We report on a set of experiments based on machine learning and crowdsourcing that show promising results.

		</bibo:abstract>

		<bibo:authorList>
			<rdf:Seq>
				<rdf:li rdf:resource="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/person/luigi_asprino" />
				<rdf:li>
					<foaf:Person rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/person/valerio_basile">
						<foaf:givenname>Valerio</foaf:givenname>
						<foaf:family_name>Basile</foaf:family_name>
					</foaf:Person>
				</rdf:li>
				<rdf:li>
					<foaf:Person rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/person/paolo_ciancarini">
						<foaf:givenname>Paolo</foaf:givenname>
						<foaf:family_name>Ciancarini</foaf:family_name>
					</foaf:Person>
				</rdf:li>
				<rdf:li>
					<foaf:Person rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/person/valentina_presutti">
						<foaf:givenname>Valentina</foaf:givenname>
						<foaf:family_name>Presutti</foaf:family_name>
					</foaf:Person>
				</rdf:li>
			</rdf:Seq>
		</bibo:authorList>
	</bibo:Article>


	<bibo:Article rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/publication/Lodi2017Semantic" dc:language="en" bibo:pageStart="3" bibo:pageEnd="37" dc:title="Semantic Web for Cultural Heritage Valorisation" dc:date="2017" bibo:doi="10.1007/978-3-319-54499-1_1">

		<dcterms:isPartOf>
			<bibo:Book rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/publication/DADH" dc:title="Data Analytics in Digital Humanities" bibo:issn="978-3-319-54499-1" />
		</dcterms:isPartOf>

		<bibo:abstract>
			Cultural heritage consists of heterogeneous resources: archaeological artefacts, monuments, sites, landscapes, paintings, photos, books and expressions of human creativity, often enjoyed in different forms: tangible, intangible or digital. Each resource is usually documented, conserved and managed by cultural institutes like museums, libraries or holders of archives. These institutes make available a detailed description of the objects as catalog records.
			In this context, the Chapter proposes both a classification of cultural heritage data types and a process for cultural heritage valorisation through the wide-spreading Linked Open Data paradigm. The classification and process have been defined in the context of a collaboration between the Semantic Technology Laboratory of
			the National Research Council (STLab) and the Italian Ministry of Cultural Heritage and Activities and Tourism (MIBACT) that the Chapter describes, although we claim they are sufficiently general to be adopted in every cultural heritage scenario.
			In particular, the Chapter introduces both a suite of ontology modules named Cultural-ON to model the principal elements identified in the cultural heritage data type classification, and the process we employed for data valorisation purposes. To this end, semantic technologies are exploited; that is, technologies that allow us to conceptualise and describe the meaning of data forming the cultural heritage and including such entities as places, institutions, cultural heritage events, availability, etc.. These entities have special characteristics
			and are connected with each other in a profound way.
			The result is a knowledge base consisting of semantic interconnections with also other data available in the Web to be exploited according to different tasks and users preferences. By navigating the semantic relationships between the various objects of the knowledge base, new semantic paths can be revealed and utilised with the aim to develop innovative services and applications.
			The process is compliant with Linked Open Data and W3C Semantic Web best practices so that to enable a wider promotion of cultural heritage, and of sharing and reuse of cultural heritage data in the Web. The Chapter concludes presenting a number of methodological principles and lessons learnt from the STLab/MIBACT collaboration that are applicable to any
			cultural heritage context and, in some cases, also to other domains.
		</bibo:abstract>

		<bibo:authorList>
			<rdf:Seq>
				<rdf:li>
					<foaf:Person rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/person/giorgia_lodi">
						<foaf:givenname>Giorgia</foaf:givenname>
						<foaf:family_name>Lodi</foaf:family_name>
					</foaf:Person>
				</rdf:li>
				<rdf:li rdf:resource="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/person/luigi_asprino" />
				<rdf:li>
					<foaf:Person rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/person/andreagiovanni_nuzzolese">
						<foaf:givenname>Andrea Giovanni</foaf:givenname>
						<foaf:family_name>Nuzzolese</foaf:family_name>
					</foaf:Person>
				</rdf:li>
				<rdf:li>
					<foaf:Person rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/person/valentina_presutti">
						<foaf:givenname>Valentina</foaf:givenname>
						<foaf:family_name>Presutti</foaf:family_name>
					</foaf:Person>
				</rdf:li>
				<rdf:li>
					<foaf:Person rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/person/aldo_gangemi">
						<foaf:givenname>Aldo</foaf:givenname>
						<foaf:family_name>Gangemi</foaf:family_name>
					</foaf:Person>
				</rdf:li>
				<rdf:li>
					<foaf:Person rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/person/diego_reforgiatorecupero">
						<foaf:givenname>Diego</foaf:givenname>
						<foaf:family_name>Reforgiato Recupero</foaf:family_name>
					</foaf:Person>
				</rdf:li>
				<rdf:li>
					<foaf:Person rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/person/chiara_veninata">
						<foaf:givenname>Chiara</foaf:givenname>
						<foaf:family_name>Veninata</foaf:family_name>
					</foaf:Person>
				</rdf:li>
				<rdf:li>
					<foaf:Person rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/person/annarita_orsini">
						<foaf:givenname>Annarita</foaf:givenname>
						<foaf:family_name>Orsini</foaf:family_name>
					</foaf:Person>
				</rdf:li>
			</rdf:Seq>
		</bibo:authorList>
	</bibo:Article>



	<cerif:Project rdf:about="https://w3id.org/ecodigit/project/ecodigit">
		<cerif:title>Ecosistema Digitale per la fruizione e la
			valorizzazione
			dei beni e delle attività culturali del Lazio
		</cerif:title>
		<cerif:acronym>EcoDigit</cerif:acronym>
		<cerif:startDate rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#date">2018-10-02</cerif:startDate>
		<cerif:endDate rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#date">2020-01-02</cerif:endDate>
		<cerif:abstract>Il progetto EcoDigit "Ecosistema Digitale per la fruizione e la valorizzazione dei beni e delle attività culturali del Lazio" è una delle iniziative del Centro di Eccellenza del Distretto Tecnologico per i beni e le attività Culturali (DTC) del Lazio, costituito dalle cinque università statali del Lazio - Sapienza, Tor Vergata, RomaTre, Cassino e Tuscia - in rete con CNR, ENEA e INFN per aggregare e integrare competenze nel settore delle tecnologie per i beni e le attività culturali. EcoDigit intende arricchire il sistema Anagrafe delle Competenze con una piattaforma middleware che faciliti l’integrazione di nuove sorgenti di dati e consenta la pubblicazione e il riuso di servizi per la valorizzazione e la fruizione del patrimonio culturale del Lazio. I principali
			obiettivi del progetto possono essere sintetizzati nei seguenti punti: 1) la prototipazione di un’architettura middleware integrata con il sistema Anagrafe per consentirgli di acquisire e integrare dati, contenuti e servizi; 2) l’identificazione e l’analisi approfondita delle sorgenti di dati e di contenuti e la progettazione di modelli comuni per la loro integrazione; 3) la progettazione di servizi avanzati e delle tecnologie e interfacce per il loro inserimento nella piattaforma comune. Il risultato finale sarà, quindi, un prototipo che dimostri le principali funzioni di supporto all’integrazione e alla fruizione. Tale prototipo intende fornire una prova di concetto e di sostenibilità della piattaforma accompagnata dalle specifiche tecniche e le metodologie per la sua messa in opera
			su larga scala.
		</cerif:abstract>
		<cerif:uri rdf:resource="http://ecodigit.dtclazio.it" />
	</cerif:Project>

</rdf:RDF>
